MD TAMZID HASAN

Phone: +880 1711 927924 | Email: thunique1988@gmail.com Research Profile: Google Scholar | Researcher ID | ResearchGate | ORCID

Social Links: Linkedin & GitHub

OBJECTIVE

To build up a career in the technical field, concentrating on research and development in order to boost production. My integrity and devotion to work motivated me to learn and share knowledge within the team, where multitasking, strong leadership, and interpersonal communication skills are most important.

ACADEMIC CREDENTIALS

Master of Public Health (MPH) | Major in Epidemiology
Department of Public Health, North South University (NSU), Bangladesh

January 2023

Masters in Electric Power Engineering (MEPE)

Department of Electrical Engineering,

August 2020

Chalmers University of Technology (CTH), Sweden | Credit Completed: 75

BSc in Electrical and Electronic Engineering

Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering, Ahsanullah University of Science and Technology (AUST), Bangladesh June 2011

Academic Research Work

- MPH thesis on "Prevalence of Myopia and Dry Eye Disease (DED) among the Digital Device Users of Female Student of North South University." Supervised by: Dr. Dipak Kumar Mitra, Professor, Department of Public Health, North South University, Dhaka, Bangladesh.
- Project work on "PTSD, Insomnia, and Suicidal Ideation among the Firefighters of Bangladesh", Study Design: Cross-sectional, Year of Study Conduct: 2023 | Funded by Bangladesh Medical Research Council (BMRC) | Principal Investigator: Dr. Mohammad Delwer Hossain Hawlader, Associate Professor & Chairman, Department of Public Health, North South University, Dhaka, Bangladesh.
- MEPE design project on "Diagnostics of a High Voltage Converter Transformer using Non-destructive Methods." Supervised by: Yuriy Serdyuk, Assistant Professor, Head of Power grids and Components, Department of Electric Power Engineering, Chalmers University of Technology.
 - Co-Supervisor: Xiangdong Xu, Researcher at Power grids and Components, Department of Electric Power Engineering, Chalmers University of Technology.
- Undergraduate thesis on "Performance Analysis of Boost Inverter for using in PV System." Supervised by: Md Jakaria Rahimi, Assistant Professor, Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering, Ahsanullah University of Science and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Consultant | Jhpiego Bangladesh (Johns Hopkins University Affiliate Responsibilities:

January 2023 – February 2024

- o Review of existing tools and literature to prepare for assessing facility readiness for the provision of maternal immunization.
- Collaboration with EPI & Surveillance, MNCAH, Directorate General of Health Services (DGHS), Ministry of Health and Family Welfare (MoHFW), Bangladesh.
- o Propose and prepare a draft new tool for assessing facility readiness for the provision of maternal immunization
- o Make a presentation to top management in 1 to 2 hours session for final feedback.
- o Train data collectors to help roll out of HF readiness tool.

Research Assistant | Global Health Institute, North South University. Responsibilities:

August 2022 – December 2023

- o Transcription and Translation of 40 IDIs, 10 KIIs, and 4 FGDs.
- o Proposal and questionnaire developing
- o Preparing a budget for the research project
- o Field survey, data monitoring, and data entry
- o Both quantitative and qualitative analysis
- o Grant proposal writing for the fund and development of the project.

Graduate Teaching Assistant | Dept. of Public Health | North South University

June 2022 - January 2023

Responsibilities:

- Assist faculty members with classroom instruction, exams, record keeping, and other miscellaneous projects and develop course plans.
- o Assist faculty members in the preparation of different module development.
- o Course curriculum development for the undergraduate students.
- O Assist academic staff with the development or update of learning materials, proctor exams, and record grades in the grade book.
- o Assist professors and department chairman with various administrative tasks.
- O Tutor or mentor students in class or outside.
- o Communicate with students and reply to their inquiries.
- o Take attendance and record responses.
- o Assist faculty members in lab class.
- o Grant proposal writing for the fund and development of the project.

Electrical Engineer | S.S. Engineering & Construction Responsibilities:

October 2013 – July 2017

- o Survey the site & manage the design and construction of electrical systems.
- o Prepare specifications for the purchase of materials and equipment.
- o Supervised and trained project team members.
- o Develop budgets, estimating labor, materials, and construction costs.

Assistant Engineer | Energy Systems (BD) Ltd. Responsibilities:

November 2011 - July 2012

- o Installation, commissioning, maintenance & designing of the solar system.
- o To assist in designing, installing, commissioning, and maintaining Solar Photovoltaic (PV) systems.
- o Prepare reports and design specifications, conduct research, and training, and supervise technicians.

JOURNAL PUBLICATION

- **4.** Md. Shafiqul Islam, Syed Muhammad Baqui Billah, Jewell Ilias Rab, Abir Dey, Md. Habib Naziat, and **Md. Tamzid Hasan** (2024): Prevalence of Diabetic Retinopathy and Associated Risk Factors in the Southern Region of Bangladesh. International Journal of Human and Health Sciences. **DOI:** http://dx.doi.org/10.31344/ijhhs.v8i2.640
- **3.** Azaz Bin Sharif, **Md Tamzid Hasan**, Syed Sharaf Ahmed Chowdhury, and Satyajit Kundu (2023): Inequalities in early initiation of breastfeeding in Bangladesh: An estimation of relative and absolute measures of inequality. International Breastfeeding Journal. **DOI:** https://doi.org/10.1186/s13006-023-00584-y
- **2.** Azaz Bin Sharif, **Md Tamzid Hasan**, Md. Habib Naziat, Tahmina Zerin, and Satyajit Kundu (2023): Permanent, long-acting, and short-acting reversible contraceptive methods use among women in Bangladesh: An analysis of Bangladesh Demographic and Health Survey 2017-2018 data. BMJ Open 2023;13:e073469. *doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-073469*
- 1. Md Jakaria Rahimi, **Md Tamzid Hasan**, Ripan Kumar Dhar, Md Shaheer Ibne Islam, Khatune Jannat Siddiqua, and Shahriar Azgar (2011): Performance Analysis of Boost Inverter for Photovoltaic System. IJETSE International Journal of Emerging Technologies in Science and Engineering, *Vol.5*, *No.2*, *Dec 2011*.

PROJECTS

- HFRA Tool | "Health Facility Readiness Assessment (HFRA) Tool for Maternal Immunization (MI) in Bangladesh" *Published by* Expanded Program on Immunization (EPI), Maternal, Neonatal, Child & Adolescent Health (MNC&AH), Directorate General of Health Services (DGHS), Ministry of Health and Family Welfare (MoHFW) Bangladesh and *Supported by* Jhpiego. | Role: Contributor to the Development of the HFRA Tool.
- MIRI Projects | Project on "Maternal Immunization Readiness Initiative (MIRI)" funded by Bill & Melinda Gates Foundation and supported by International Vaccine Access Center (IVAC) and initiated by Jhpiego Bangladesh. | Role: Consultant.

SKILLS

Operating Systems: Microsoft Windows & MacOS **Data Analysis and Data Visualization:** R, RStudio

Other Software Skills: MS Office (Word, Excel, and Power point), LaTeX